Hello English learners, welcome back to
English Pod. My name is Marco and I'm Erica
and today we are going back in time again
and this time we're going to be in the 1960s.
That's right, we're going
to learn some phrases and
some slang that were
really popular back in 1964.
Exactly, and most of these
phrases and words we still
use today so it's very interesting
and very good to know.
That's right, I'm looking
forward to this trip back in
time, so why don't we get
started with the dialogue.
All right, so great
dialogue, very popular in the
60s, the music, the mood
and the words, right?
That's right, so why don't we
get down to business and look at
the vocabulary that we saw in
this dialogue in language takeaway.
Language takeaway, well
the dialogue opened and we
heard this guy say, "Hey
man, I really like your pad.
" I really like your pad. Pad. Okay,
so pad, a very informal way of saying?
Your apartment, your apartment, right?
And now you can still use it today.
Yeah, that's right, we often
hear the expression, "Bachler pad.
" Okay, a bachelor pad. So that's an
apartment where a single man lives.
Okay, so a bachelor
pad, usually it's very nicely
decorated and really a
nice apartment, right?
Or maybe it has empty pizza
boxes all over the form or go.
Also a bachelor pad, but so that's
what pad means in apartment.
They were talking about the apartment
and he said, "The lava lamps are far out.
" Okay, it's far out.
So that's really cool or amazing.
Right, and lava lamps, those are
those strange cone-looking lamps, right?
Kind of a light with some liquid
moving inside, very popular in the 60s.
Yeah, we'll post some pictures of that.
Yeah, and the lamps are far out, so now
you can use that with other things, right?
Like, you are really far out.
Yeah, or this music is really far out.
It kind of gives you the
feeling like it's sort of spacey.
Spacey. Yeah.
All right, so the
pad is really far out,
the lava lamps are
great, and he was saying,
"Thanks for letting
me crash here tonight.
" Too crash.
So to crash at someone's place.
Right, so we're not talking
about like a car crash.
Yeah, no, no.
But so when you crash
somewhere, what do you do?
Well, you are staying there, then
you're going to stay there, as a guest.
Yeah, so like sleep, right?
Yeah, and for free.
For free, yes.
So if, for example, you're going
to New York and you're going
to visit a friend, you might
crash at your friend's house.
That's right, so interesting word,
and it is quite commonly used now.
So why don't we hear some
examples of how we can use it?
Example one.
Hey man, can I crash at your place tonight?
Example two.
I lost my keys, so I'm crashing
at my girlfriend's house.
Example three.
No, you've been sleeping
on my couch for a month.
You're not going to crash here tonight.
All right, perfect.
So to crash, right?
It's still commonly used today.
Yeah.
Now for the fourth word, groovy.
Groovy.
That would be groovy.
So again, this means like
great or cool or really nice.
Yeah, this is, I think this is one
of the main words of the 1960s.
Something was groovy.
Yes, I agree.
So it kind of gives you the sense that it's
sort of really cool, but in a relaxed way.
Yeah, it's groovy.
This music is really groovy.
That's right.
And finally, his friend, he said,
hey, I got a split for a while.
Two splits?
Okay, so if I say I have to split.
You have to leave.
I have to leave.
Yeah.
Very colloquial.
Mm-hmm.
And it means I have
to leave for a little bit.
Yeah.
Split for a while.
That's right.
You may not have heard this one before.
So why don't we hear some examples
to help you understand how it's used?
Example one.
Hurry up.
We've got a split before
the police get here.
Example two.
This party is boring.
Let's split.
Example three.
I have to wake up early
tomorrow, so we're going to split.
Okay, very good.
So split.
Now, also, I think you can
use it for relationships, right?
Me and him.
Yeah.
Me and her split up.
That's right.
Okay, so we saw five really
common phrases from the 1960s.
Let's listen to the dialogue again.
A little bit slower.
And then we'll come back and
look at some phrases from the 60s.
Hey, man.
I really like your pad.
Those lava lamps are far out.
Thanks for letting me crash here tonight.
It's no problem, brother.
I wanted a pad where people could
come, listen to music, and just hang loose.
You dig what I'm saying?
I dig it, man.
We could throw a bash here and
make it a really happening scene.
Yeah, man.
That would be groovy.
Hey, I got a split for a while.
Are you okay here by yourself?
Don't worry about me, brother.
You could take care of your business.
All right.
Peace out.
Well, I want to get started at
looking up these 1960s slang phrases.
So let's go now with putting it together.
Putting it together.
All right.
I'm putting it together today.
Let's start with the first part.
He talked about you dig what I'm saying.
I dig it, man.
You dig what I'm saying?
Two digots.
All right.
So we know the verb dig, which
means to make a hole, right?
Yeah.
But now he's talking about understand.
Basically, you dig what I'm saying.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
And when he says I dig
it, he says I understand.
Yeah.
Okay.
Now, there's also another
meaning to this, right?
Apart from understand.
Yeah.
It can also mean I like it.
Okay.
So I really dig this type of music.
Or I really dig this restaurant.
Okay.
I kind of like it.
All right.
Now moving on, he said
we could throw a bash here.
All right.
Throw a bash.
To throw a bash.
So first of all, what is a bash?
A bash is a party.
A really great party.
An amazing party.
Now, I want to look at this
verb to throw something.
So we know that you throw a ball, right?
Right.
But how can you throw a party?
Well, it's basically saying you
organize or you host a party.
Okay.
And how can you use this phrase?
So I can say last week, I threw
a birthday party in my house.
Okay.
Or let's throw a bash to
celebrate your engagement.
Okay.
Or next week, I'm going to
throw a dinner party at my house.
Okay.
So to throw a party.
And it's usually used for parties, right?
Right.
Throw a meeting.
All right.
No.
Okay.
So now we heard them use
the word man a lot, right?
Hey, man.
Yeah, that's right.
Now, this is so common even in modern
English that I think we need some examples.
Example one.
Hey, man.
Watch where you're going.
Example two.
Yeah, man.
That's a great idea.
Example three.
Man, that was awesome.
So man is one of those words that
you just use at the end of your sentences.
Or at the beginning.
And so you say, hey, man, or yeah, man.
Yeah.
But what about, do you
have to be a man to use it?
Or do you have to be
talking to a man to use it?
No, not really.
Men and women use the word man.
Yeah.
And you can call a girl.
Like, hey, man, how are you?
Yeah, but that sort of means that
she's a really, really good friend.
Like the same level of
friend as your guy, friends.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Okay.
Very good.
And now for the last
phrase, I'm putting it together.
He said, you go take care of business.
To take care of business.
Okay.
So I have to take care of business.
So we're not really talking
about business and work here.
No, no, no.
So basically what we're
saying is go handle your affairs.
So do the things you have to do.
Okay.
So or solve your problems.
So if I say, I have to go to City Hall
today and take care of some business.
So you're maybe going to do something
like pay my taxes or something like that.
Yeah.
Okay.
So to take care of business.
So we heard some great phrases.
We saw these words.
Let's listen to the
dialogue for the last time.
And then we'll come back
and talk about this great decade.
Hey, man.
I really like your path.
There's a lot of events are far out.
Thanks for learning to crash here tonight.
There's no problem, brother.
I wanted a pad where people could
come, listen to music and just hang loose.
You take what I'm saying.
I dig it, man.
We should do a bash here and
make it really happening seen.
Yeah, man.
That would be groovy.
Hey, I got a split for a while.
Are you okay here by yourself?
Don't worry about me, brother.
You could take care of your business.
All right.
Peace out.
So 1960s, very famous among rock music,
the piece and conflicts and all this stuff.
Yeah, that's right.
And I guess in English or Anglo pop culture,
we look back at this decade very fondly.
Yeah.
And also we really related
to the hippie movement.
Yeah, yeah.
People with long hair and baggy clothes.
Yeah.
You know, living in their cars,
going from concert to concert.
Yeah.
And I mean, speaking of
music, I think if we think 1960s,
at least in Anglo world, in the Anglo
world, we think of the best music.
Like, I think this is the golden age of
music in English speaking countries.
Yes, it was a very good era.
And well, what do you guys think?
Do you think the '60s was the best decade
or maybe you are more
fond of the '70s, the disco era?
Or even the '90s, there's
some pretty good music in 1994.
Exactly.
So come to our website and
let us know what you think.
And also if you have any
questions or comments.
Marco and I are always
around to answer your questions.
So thanks for downloading.
And until next time, bye.
Bye.